# James Rosenthal

(a) +1.520.780.2868 ⋈ jamesdrosenthal@gmail.com idrosenthal.com

## Summary

I am a Ph.D. student in electrical engineering with experience in embedded systems, RF design, and communication systems. I have worked on biomedical, consumer, and aerospace systems across the product life-cycle. I am a US citizen and am eligible for employment within the USA.

#### Education

2018-Present Ph.D., Electrical & Computer Engineering, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA.

Advisor: Prof. Matthew S. Reynolds

Research Focus: Ultra-low power embedded communication systems for neural implants

NSF Graduate Research Fellow, GPA: 3.94/4.00, (J1-J3, C3-C7)

Teaching Assistant: Intro to Digital Design, Technical Writing, Advanced Topics in Comms

2016-2018 Master's of Science, Electrical & Computer Engineering, University of Washington,

Seattle, WA, USA.

GPA: 3.93/4.00

2008-2013 Bachelor's of Science, Electrical Engineering, University of Minnesota-Twin Cities, MN,

USA.

GPA: 3.73/4.00

### Work Experience

Spring 2019 ViaSat Tempe, AZ

RF Engineering Intern

Design, simulation, analysis, and testing of K-band RF circuitry for satellite internet.

#### Summer 2017 NASA Langley Research Center Hampton, VA

Electrical Engineer

Design, fabrication, and testing of a custom nanosatellite flight computer board.

2013-2016 NASA Langley Research Center Hampton, VA

Electrical Engineer

Hardware and systems design for terrestrial and stratospheric flight systems. Served as lead avionics engineer for the Radiation Dosimetry Experiment (C2) high-altitude balloon and the On-orbit Autonomous Assembly of Nanosatellite (C1) projects.

2013 Synapse Product Development Seattle, WA

Electrical Engineering Intern

Design, fabrication, and testing of consumer electronics.

2012 Airbus Toulouse, France

Electrical Engineering Intern

Research and development of a CDMA wireless modem implemented on FPGAs.

2011-2012 University of Minnesota UAV Research Group Minneapolis, MN

Research Assistant

Design, fabrication, and testing of sensors for drones. Flew specific flight patterns as the drone test pilot for research on controls and system identification.

#### Summer 2010 University of Arizona Neurorobotics Laboratory Tucson, AZ

Research Assistant

Firmware and instrumentation engineer working on humanoid robots.

#### 2009 University of Minnesota UAV Research Group Minneapolis, MN

Research Assistant

Instrumentation engineer and flight test pilot of fixed-wing and rotary-wing research drones.

# Grants & Scholarships

- 2019 Bergstrom Award for Art & Science, Co-Investigator
- 2018 National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellow (NSF GRFP)
- 2018 NASA Space Technology Research Fellowship (declined for NSF GRFP)
- 2011 Roger M. Nordby Engineering Scholarship
- 2009 New Look Laser Technologies Essay Scholarship Winner
- 2008 Academy of Model Aeronautics Student Achievement Scholarship
- 2008-2012 University of Minnesota Gopher Gold Scholarship

#### Honors

- 2019 IEEE Wireless Sensor Networks Conference Student Paper Award Finalist (C4 & C5)
- 2017 NASA Group Achievement Award Autonomy Incubator
- 2016 NASA Group Achievement Award Radiation Dosimetry Experiment (C2)

## Peer-Reviewed Publications (J-journal, C-conference)

- J3 J. Rosenthal and M.S. Reynolds, "A 1.0 Mbps 198 pJ/bit Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) Compatible Single Sideband Backscatter Uplink for the NeuroDisc Brain-Computer Interface," IEEE Trans. on Microwave Theory and Techniques, 2019.
- J2 **J. Rosenthal**, A. Sharma, E. Kampianakis, M.S. Reynolds, "A 25 Mbps, 12.4 pJ/bit Backscatter Data Uplink for the NeuroDisc Brain Computer Interface," *IEEE Trans. on Biomedical Circuits and Systems*, 2019.
- J1 A. Sharma, E. Kampianakis, J. Rosenthal, A. Pike, A. Dadkhah, and M.S. Reynolds, "Wideband UHF DQPSK Backscatter Communications in Reverberant Cavity Animal Cage Environments," *IEEE Trans. on Antennas and Propagation*, 2019.
- C7 L. Arjona, **J. Rosenthal**, J.R. Smith, and C.T. Moritz, "High Performance Flexible Protocol for Backscattered-based Neural Implants," *ICEAA IEEE Antennas and Propagation in Wireless Comms. Conference*, 2019.
- C6 J. Rosenthal, A. Pike, and M.S. Reynolds, "A 1 Mbps 158 pJ/bit Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) Compatible Backscatter Communication Uplink for Wireless Neural Recording in an Animal Cage Environment," *IEEE Conference on RFID*, 2019.
- C5 **J. Rosenthal** and M.S. Reynolds, "A 158 pJ/bit 1.0 Mbps Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) Compatible Backscatter Communication System for Wireless Sensing," *IEEE Topical Conference on Wireless Sensors and Sensor Networks (WiSNet)*, 2019.
- C4 A. Dadkhah, **J. Rosenthal**, and M.S. Reynolds, "ZeroScatter: Zero-Added-Component Backscatter Communication using Existing Digital I/O Pins," *IEEE Topical Conference on Wireless Sensors and Sensor Networks (WiSNet)*, 2019.

- C3 **J. Rosenthal**, A. Sharma, E. Kampianakis, and M.S. Reynolds, "A 6.25 Mbps, 12.4 pJ/bit DQPSK Backscatter Wireless Uplink for the NeuroDisc Brain-Computer Interface," *IEEE International Conference on Biomedical Circuits and Systems (BioCAS)*, 2018.
- C2 **J. Rosenthal**, B. Hayes, and C. Mertens. "A Silicon Micro Dosimeter for High-Altitude Measurements of Cosmic Radiation," *IEEE Aerospace Conference*, 2018.
- C1 J. Pei, L. Murchison, A. Ben Shabat, V. Stewart, **J. Rosenthal**, et al. "Ground Demonstration on the Autonomous Docking of Two 3U Cubesats using a Novel Permanent-Magnet Docking Mechanism." *AIAA Aerospace Sciences Meeting*, 2017.

# Posters, Presentations, and Demos

- Presentation "A 1 Mbps 158 pJ/bit Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) Compatible Backscatter Communication Uplink for Wireless Neural Recording in an Animal Cage Environment," *IEEE Conference on RFID*, 2019.
- Presentation "A 158 pJ/bit 1.0 Mbps Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) Compatible Backscatter Communi-+ Poster cation System for Wireless Sensing," *IEEE WiSNet*, 2019.
- Presentation "A 6.25 Mbps, 12.4 pJ/bit DQPSK Backscatter Wireless Uplink for the NeuroDisc Brain+Poster Computer Interface." *IEEE BioCAS*, 2018.
- Presentation "A Silicon Micro Dosimeter for High-Altitude Measurements of Cosmic Radiation." *IEEE Aerospace Conference*, 2018.
  - Poster "Fully Wireless Instrumentation for a Bi-Direction BCI," NeuroFutures Conference, 2018.
  - Demo "IBPoet: An Interactive & Biosensitive Poetry Composition Device," in *ACM UbiComp Conference*, 2017.
  - Poster "Aerodynamic Characterization of the Mini Ultra Stick Airframe." *National Conference for Undergraduate Research*, 2012.
  - Demos Numerous demos and informal presentations for fundraising, lab visitors, and outreach guests.

#### Volunteering & Outreach

- 2018 UW Summer Youth Electronics Design, Instructor
- 2018 UW GEARUP, Outreach Presenter
- 2017-Present **UW** Engineering Days, Outreach Presenter
- 2018-Present **UW** Graduate and Professional Student Senate, Senator
  - 2016-2018 UW EE Graduate Student Association, President
    - 2017 **UW** EE Soldering Workshop, Instructor
  - 2016-2018 Washington State Opportunities Scholar Program, Mentor
    - 2016 **Big Brothers Big Sisters**, Mentor
  - 2013-2016 **NASA** *HUNCH* Outreach Mentor, providing hands-on experience to students building space-flight hardware
    - 2015 NASA Virtual Career Fair, Speaker
    - 2018 NASA RaD-X Outreach, Presenter
  - 2013-2016 NASA Speaker's Bureau, Volunteer speaker at local schools and libraries
  - 2014-2016 NASA College of William & Mary's Focus on the Future, Volunteer speaker
    - 2013 International Rescue Committee, Refugee Resettlement, Volunteer

# Technical Experience

Programming Matlab (proficient), Verilog, Embedded C (basic), Python (basic), BASH (basic)

Software Altium Designer, Eagle CAD, LTSpice, HFSS, ADS, CST (basic)

Protocols Bluetooth Low Energy, UART, SPI, I2C, CAN, USB

Lab Proficient with circuit prototyping and debugging, Network Analyzers, Spectrum Analyzers,

Equipment Oscilloscopes, Multimeters, Soldering (through-hole, surface-mount)

Testing Thermal Vacuum Chamber, Burn-in, Radiation Beam Calibration, IACUC-approved Animal

Experience Testing

# Languages & Outside Interests

English Fluent

French Negotiation Level

Flying FAA Private Pilot Glider Certificate (Current)

HAM Radio FCC Technician Class License (KK4VMN)